A Guide to the Rockefeller Family Public Relations Department papers, Series 10-12 FA789
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Family Public Relations Department papers, Series 10-12
1946-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller family
FA789
11.24 Cubic Feet
Biographical / Historical
After World War II the Rockefeller family office grew rapidly as John D. Rockefeller Jr.'s sons began actively working in the office. One new department established in 1946 was that of Public Relations.
Under the direction of Francis A. Jamieson the Public Relations department initially spent most of its efforts on Nelson A. Rockefeller's Latin American activities. The department also prepared press releases and offered public relations advise to the other brothers and occasionally for JDR Jr.
In many ways the department also became the eyes and ears of the office. Two newspaper clipping services were engaged as well as a radio monitoring service. The clippings and reports were circulated among the five brothers and clipping scrapbooks -- which appear in the collection as series 2 and 3 -- were made.
As the activities of the brothers grew during the 1950s and 1960s the Public Relations department was given increasing responsibilities in the preparation of family and office policy toward a great variety of social, economic and cultural activities. To provide sufficient background on this expanding universe the department established research files which were maintained by staff.
The department also collected periodical literature containing articles about or of interest to the Rockefellers. This literature was not systematically collected or compiled. The PR department also inherited a backlog of magazine articles from the files of various administrative assistants. One important source of back periodicals that are now included in this collection are the files kept by Robert W. Gumbel, once private secretary to JDR Jr. and later office manager.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Other Finding Aids
FA789A Rockefeller Family Public Relations Department papers, Series 1-9
FA1193 Rockefeller Family Public Relations Department papers, Series 13
FA329 Office of the Messrs. Rockefeller records, Public Relations, Series T
Scope and Contents
The Public Relations Department papers document the general activities and public opinion of the Rockefeller family during the years 1946-1961.
- Printed Materials, 1897-1992; 10
  - The Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Memorial Window, Union Church of Pocantico Hills (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - One Beekman Place: Plan of Organization, Schedules, Agreement for Purchase of Stock (signed by Abby Milton and David Milton), c. 1930 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - One Beekman Place: Proprietary Lease and House Rules (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - One Beekman Place: Brochure (Box 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Including floor plans and description of amenities.
  - Rockefeller Center. Color brochure, circa 1932., c. 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Memorial Service for Mrs. John D. Rockefeller. Jr. (Abby Aldrich Rockefeller), Riverside Church, 1948 May 23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Rockefeller, Ann C. 'Remarks by Miss Ann C. Rockefeller at the service on Sunday, December 26, 1954 in the Union Church of Pocantico, 1954 December 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - In Memorium: Blanchette Ferrv Hooker Rockefeller, 1909-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dinner given by The Chase Manhattan Bank N.A. in honor of Mr. Makoto Usami, Governor, The Bank of Japan, at The Knickerbocker Club, New York, 1966 October (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Mr. David Rockefeller, Chairman of the Board, Chase Manhattan Bank, N.A, host.
  - Luncheon given by Mr. and Mrs. George Champion, Mr. and Mrs. David Rockefeller in honor of Special Delegates Attending the 1968 Annual Meetings of the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development and the International Monetary Fund at The Playhouse, Pocantico Hills, New York, 1968 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Luncheon given by Mr. and Mrs. David Rockefeller in honor of Special Delegates attending the 1969 Annual Meetings of the International Bank for the Reconstruction and Development and the International Monetary Fund at The Playhouse, Pocantico Hills, New York, 1969 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dinner in honor of Mr. Tadashi Sasaki, Governor, Bank of Japan, hosted by Mr. David Rockefeller, Chairman of the Board, Chase Manhattan Bank, N.A. The Knickerbocker Club, New York, 1971 September 23 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    JDR 3rd guest.
  - Rockefeller, John D. First Ledger - of a successful - Man of Affairs: Mr. Rockefeller's Ledger, The First He Kept and What Was In It, Saving Money and Early Giving. Delivered at a Social Gathering of The Young Men's Bible Class of the Park Avenue Baptist Church, 1897 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Saturday evening
  - Rockefeller, John D. Early Experiences of A Young Business Man: A Plain Talk by a Plain Man. At The Club of The Young Men's Bible Class of the Fifth Avenue Baptist Church (The Riverside Church), 1904 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Holliday, W. Trevor. John D. Rockefeller (1839-1937) Industrial Pioneer and Man. New York: The Newcomen Society of England, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rockefeller, John D. Jr. Statement of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Before United States Commission on Industrial Relations, 1915 January 25 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Rockefeller, John D. Jr. Remarks of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. at the National Industrial Conference, Washington, D.C., 1919 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Morrow, Mrs. Dwight and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. The Elements of Success in Soliciting for a Cause. The Citizens Family Welfare Committee of New York City, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mr. John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s Proposed Gift of Land for the National Park System in Wyoming. History of the Snake River Land Company and of the Efforts to Preserve the Jackson Hole Country for the Nation. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Rockefeller, John D. Jr. Character, The Foundation of Successful Business. An address delivered before the Twenty-Six Broadway Club, 1947 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Rockefeller, John D. Jr. Tribute of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. to his Father. New York, N.Y.: Chamber of Commerce. An Address before the Chamber of Commerce of the State of New York upon the occasion of the election of Mr. Rockefeller as an Honorary Member, 1950 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - In Memorium: John D. Rockefeller, Jr., John D. Rockefeller family Cemetery, Tarrytown, NY, 1960 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Memorial Service for John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., 1960 June 8 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Rockefeller, John D. 3rd. Our Opportunity, An Address by John D. Rockefeller 3rd, Colonial Williamsburg, Williamsburg, Virginia - Remarks at Meeting of Employees, 1948 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Wednesday
  - The Rockefeller Foundation, Fiftieth Anniversarv Dinner. Addresses by J. George Harrar, John D. Rockefeller, 3rd and The Honorable Dean Rusk. The Plaza, New York, 1963 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Rockefeller, John D. 3rd. Philanthropy in Our Changing World. An address by John D. Rockefeller, 3rd at the Inaugural Dinner of the Federation of Jewish Philanthropies of New York, Plaza Hotel, New York City, 1964 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Rockefeller, John D. 3rd. Needed: A Fresh Approach for the Public Service. Address given by John D. Rockefeller, 3rd at Presentation of the Public Service Awards, Shoreham Hotel, Washington, D. C., 1968 December 4 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Rockefeller, John D. 3rd. New Beginnings: Inaugural Address by John D. Rockefeller 3rd: Inauguration Ceremonies for 12th President John D. Rockefeller IV, Buckhannon, West Virginia: West Virginia Wesleyan College, 1973 September 28 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Includes speaker introduction.
  - Rockefeller, John 3rd. New Beginnings: Watergate and the Bicentennial. Speech delivered on the occasion of the inauguration of John D. Rockefeller, IV as president of West Virginia Wesleyan College, Buckhannon, West Virginia, 1973 September 28 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - In Memorium: John D. Rockefeller, 3rd, 1906-1978. Riverside Church, New York City, 1978 July 13 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Thursday, 11am
  - The Proposed Incorporation of the Rockefeller Foundation in the District of Columbia, 1912 March 15 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Certain Documents and Newspaper Comment Concerning Annual Election of the Board of Directors Standard Oil Company of Indiana, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Colonel Stewart and the Standard Oil Company of Indiana, A Letter to the Stockholders of the Company from Winthrop W. Aldrich, 1929 February 8 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Extracts from Editorial Comment on the Effort to Secure Proxies to be Voted at the Annual Meeting of the Standard Oil Company of Indiana. New York City: Equitable Trust Company, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Additional Extracts from Editorial Comment on the Effort to Secure Proxies to be Voted at the Annual Meeting of the Standard Oil Company of Indiana. New York City: Equitable Trust Company, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - The Dedication of the University Chapel. The University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, 1928 October 28 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - French, John, Jr. Leisure and Values. A Commencement Address, Dartmouth, Class of 1930 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Thompson, C. S. Thomas Hooker - The Predecessor of Thomas Jefferson in Democracy. The Cheshire Chronicle Press. Cheshire, CT, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Harrar, J. George. Foundations and the Future. New York: The Rockefeller Foundation. Presented at the Seventeenth Annual Conference of the Council on Foundations, Inc., Denver, Colorado, 1966 May 11 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - The Artwork at Jackson Lake Lodge, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Service for Francis A. Jamieson. Conducted by Rev. Walter D. Kring, The Unitarian Church of All Souls at The Funeral Church, New York, NY, 1960 February 1 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Monday
  - Loehr, Max. Buddhist Thought and Imagery. The Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Inaugural Lecture. Cambridge: Harvard University, 1961 February 24 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Partners in Progress: Summarv of a Report to the President by The International Development Advisory Board. New York, 1951 March (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Tableaux Sculptures. John D. Rockefeller, 3rd, Works of Art (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - The Abby Aldrich Rockefeller Memorial Window, Union Church of Pocantico Hills, Duplicates (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Rockefeller, John D. Early Experiences of A Young Business Man: A Plain Talk by a Plain Man. At The Club of The Young Men's Bible Class of the Fifth Avenue Baptist Church (The Riverside Church), Saturday Evening, 1904 May 7; Duplicates (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Rockefeller, John D., Jr. Statement of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. Before United States Commission on Industrial Relations, 1915 January 25; Duplicates (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rockefeller, John D., Jr. Remarks of John D. Rockefeller, Jr. at the National Industrial Conference, Washington, D.C., 1919 October 19; Duplicates (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - In Memorium: John D. Rockefeller, Jr. May 15, 1960, John D. Rockefeller Family Cemetery, Tarrytown, N.Y., 1960 May 15; Duplicates (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - In Memorium: Blanchette Ferry Hooker Rockefeller, 1909-1992, Duplicates (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - EnGuardia, Volume I, 5 volumes, 5 Volumes (Box 4)
  - EnGuardia, Volume II, 5 Volumes (Box 5)
  - En Guardia, Volume III, 5 Volumes (Box 6)
  - En Guardia, Volume III (Box 7)
  - En Guardia, Embossed Copies, Em Guardo, En Guard (Box 8)
  - En Guardia, Embossed Copies, Em Guardo, En Guard (Box 9)
  - En Guardia, Embossed Copies, Em Guardo, En Guard (Box 10)
- Press Releases, 1946-1977; 11; 2 Reels 2 microform reels.
  Arrangement
  Chronological
  - Press Releases, 1946 April 29-1959 December 23 (Reel 1)
  - Press Releases, 1960 January-1977 October (Reel 2)
- Press Clippings - Scrapbooks, 1953-1962; 12; 3 Reels 3 microform reels.
  - Press Clippings - Scrapbooks, 1953-1956 (Reel 1)
  - Press Clippings - Scrapbooks, 1956 December-1958 April (Reel 2)
  - Press Clippings - Scrapbooks, 1958 May-1962 April (Reel 3)